Ahmad Nayyar Hassan . Jarvis Consulting

Around two years of working experience in the field of data analytics and software development. My expertise lies towards Java programming and big data. I have sound analytical and data engineering capabilities and hands on experience with database management using SQL and various machine learning algorithms using R and python. I have demonstrated strong communication and leadership skills through successful extracurricular initiatives and team lead role within a few months of professional experience.

Skills

Proficient: Java, Bash, SQL, Python, Spark, Docker, Keras, Machine Learning, Data Analysis, Statistics, Software Development

Competent: Maven, C++, MATLAB, Docker, Jenkins, Hadoop, Tableau, Mockito

Familiar: AWS, MongoDB, Spring Framework, ETL

Development Projects

Project source code:https://github.com/jarviscanada/jarvis_data_eng_ahmad/tree/develop

- Linux & SQL:: Developed a cluster management solution using Bash to record hardware specifications and periodically monitor resource usages of individual nodes in a cluster of servers. Used Docker instantiated RDBMS PostgreSQL database for data persistence. Gathered and registered real time data in the database instance using crontab jobs.
- Java Grep: Implemented Unix grep command in Java using Stream API and Lambda Expressions.
- Java JDBC: Developed an application using JDBC along with PostgreSQL to provide abstraction using different design patterns. Used both DAO(Data Access Object) and Repository pattern to provide abstraction on database/data files incorporating complex joins and queries.
- Twitter CLI App: Used MVC architecture to implement a twitter application which allows user to Post, Delete and show Tweets through command line. Performed unit testing using Mockito framework and handled database interactions through JDBC. Managed dependencies of different layers within the application using Spring Boot framework.

Professional Experiences

Data Engineer, Jarvis, Toronto (2020-Present): Develop Linux and Java-based applications with *maven* automation tool. These applications handling databases through JDBC and interacting with *REST* APIs such as of Twitter. Unit testing is performed using Mockito framework and auto-configuration of dependencies files is done using *Spring Boot* framework.

Data Scientist, LUMS, Lahore (2017-2018): Performed exploratory data analysis using *Tableau*, data pre-processing using Python and data base management using MySQL.Carried out telecom coverage analysis using Machine Learning Algorithms including SVR (Support Vector Regression), ANN (Artificial Neural Network) with *Keras, Tensor Flow* and Outlier Detection through cluster-based approaches including K-Means clustering and DBSCAN. Managed and guided a team of full and part-time researchers.

Education & Academic Projects

University of Waterloo (2018-2019), Master of Engineering, Computer Engineering

- Sale Price Prediction: Designed an end to end Machine Learning Pipeline(object-oriented) to predict the price of item listings on online shopping platform. Developed front end **REST API** using **flask** framework, used Jenkins for designing Continuous Integration/Continuous Deployment (**CI/CD**) pipeline and deployed the model on the **AWS-EC2** platform using **Docker** for containerization. The proposed architecture achieved a RMSE (Root Mean Squared Error) of 0.241
- Data Mining on Yelp Dataset: Analyzed Yelp Data to find patterns and perform customer analytics. Set-up
 and stored data in MySQL server database. Wrote complex and nested queries to perform data cleaning and extract
 meaningful customer information. Performed CRUD Operations, imposed sanity and consistency conditions. Added

indexes for efficient data querying and created ER . Implemented both the $Decision\ Tree\ Classifier$ and $Naive\ Bayes$ Predictor as stored procedures in MySQL through an interactive GUI in Python.

- Page Rank in PySpark: Performed graph analysis using a graph of Gnutella server network. Implemented single source personalized page rank and handled dead end and spider trap problems using *Spark*.
- Web Traffic Time Series Forecasting:Built a prediction model using LSTM neural network to estimate future web traffic on distinct Wikipedia pages.Performed in depth exploratory data analysis (*EDA*) to detect trends and seasonality in the data using pandas, seaborn and matplotlib. Performed differencing to achieve stationarity and used Augmented Dicky fuller test to identify it.Developed a LSTM model with baseline *ARIMA* model, the MAPE score improved significantly from 8.2 to 7.27 percent.

Lahore University of Management Science (2013-2017), Bachelor of Applied Science, Electrical Engineering

• Optimized installation of security cameras at traffic intersections: Developed Python and C++ computerbased application for the local police to optimize the number of street traffic cameras by solving the vertex cover.Integrated python scripts with C++ using inter process communication via piping, multi threading and solved vertex cover problem using SAT solvers.

Certificates & Awards & Activities

- Dean's Honor List ,2017
- DataCamp: Big Data Fundamentals via PySpark, Supervised Learning with scikit-learn, Unsupervised learning in Python, Deep Learning in Python, Statistical Thinking in Python, Python Data Science Toolbox (1 and 2)
- Udemy: The Ultimate Hands on Hadoop
- Director Debates Society, 2017